# Venkata Rajesh Kumar

 $\bigcirc$  rajesh-git | in rajesh-kumar |  $\searrow$  venkatrajk079@gmail.com |  $\bigcirc$  +1-312-975-3547

## SUMMARY

I'm a software engineer with 4.5 years of experience in developing web apps and services. I am a team player who is passionate about engineering, design, and building products that solve real-world problems and influence improving the day-to-day lives of people. I'm always looking for new ways to learn and grow. For details, click here.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

# University of Missouri Student Developer

Oct 2022 - Dec 2023

Kansas City, MO

- Worked on the development of web portals for university applications using Angular and ASP.NET.
- Integrated Angular with RESTful APIs to enable real-time inventory tracking in the student management system.
- Contributed to increased code reusability by creating a shared Angular component library used across multiple university applications.
- Implemented OAuth 2.0 JWT token authorization for .NET REST APIs to ensure secure authentication and access control.
- Improved Web API performance by 60% through the utilization of Multi-threading concepts, Memory Caching, and Pagination techniques.
- Wrote integration tests for APIs utilizing the X-unit assembly framework, achieving an 85% coverage.
- Participating in weekly code reviews and pair programming sessions to enhance the development team's overall efficiency and code quality.

#### RENAULT-NISSAN-MITSUBISHI

May 2020 - Jul 2022

#### Software Engineer

Chennai, India

- Spreadhead the design and Implementation of (Nissan) after sales division application with C#,
  ASP.NET 5.0 MVC, driving a 40% boost in system efficiency and slashing operational costs by 30%.
- Used AJAX in Razor Views for async HTTP calls to Action methods, employing JavaScript promises and callbacks to send/receive data without page reloads.
- Crafted responsive dynamic Views, HTML helpers, data annotation attributes in MVC to improve code modularity and reusability, resulting in 20% reductions in development time.
- Handled DOM manipulation with JavaScript events to dynamically update View page content and created custom events, client-side validation rules.
- Designed and Implemented ASP.NET MVC routing to define URL patterns, direct requests to controllers/actions, and establish RESTful APIs for seamless client-server communication.
- Designed and implemented data model using Entity Framework as the persistence layer and performed LINQ to SQL queries.
- Written SQL Server database objects, enhancing system reliability by 30% and reducing data-related issues by 15%.
- Collaborated with devops team in setting up Azure CI/CD pipelines to automate build and test and deploy in Azure App Service.

#### Graduate Software Engineer

Jan 2019 - May 2020

- Involved in analyzing, coding, testing, implementation, creating documentation and maintaining software applications, accordance to the requirement.
- Used Angular 8 to develop single page applications, worked with Ngrx for managing data in applications.
- Created Typescript reusable components to consume REST API's. Defined Component-based architecture using Angular Structural Directives, Component decorator, Interceptors, services etc.
- Used RxJS library to manage concurrency when fetching data through HTTP calls using Observables.
- Developed Web APIs for PLM Software tools in microservice architecture by following SOA, Microsoft Design pattern's, Dependency Injection.
- Implemented Core .NET concepts like Middleware's, Exception handlings, Filters, Handlers, and Collections to an API.
- Applied Object Oriented Programming principles and developed C# Extension and Generic factory methods.
- Applied asynchronous programming techniques when dealing with long running tasks decreases response time by 70%.
- Utilized MS Build as build automation tool and responsible for GITLAB CI/CD process implementation using Jenkins and deployed artifacts on Renault private Cloud.
- Achieved 90%-unit test coverage with Jasmine/Karma and N-unit, reducing bugs and enhancing production readiness.
- Engaged in Agile scrum activities and participated in sprint planning, backlog grooming and responsible for stand-ups.

## **SLN Technologies**

Aug 2018 - Nov 2018

#### **Engineer Intern**

Chennai, India

- Crafted a responsive full-stack web app using ASP.NET Web API backend and Angular frontend, enabling CRUD operations and hosting on IIS Express.
- Proficient in writing unit tests with MOQ framework, debugging with Swagger & Postman, and conducting P2P reviews.

## SKILLS

Programming C#, TypeScript, JavaScript, SQL Script, Power Shell & Python

Web Technologies Angular 16, .NET Core, .NET Framework, ASP.NET 7.0, Signal R, ORM frame-

work, HTML, CSS, JSON, XML, Playwright framework

Databases & Cloud

MS SQL Server, Mongo DB, Microsoft Azure services

Windows Apps

Winforms, WPF, Microsoft Power Apps

Tools GIT, Jenkins, Serilog Splunk, Log 4j, ARAS, Visual Studio

## EDUCATION

2022 - 2023 Master's Degree at University of Missouri at Kansas City (GPA: 3.8/4.0) 2015 - 2019 Bachelor's Degree at Sathyabama Insistute of Science & Technology (GPA: 3.5/4.0)

## CERTIFICATIONS

- Certified as Azure Associate Developer (AZ-204) and C# programming from Microsoft.
- Achieved certification as a RESTful API Designer, and API Security Architect by API Academy.
- Trained and Certified as an ARAS Innovator Developing Solutions.

# PROJECTS

- Developed RESTful API services and integrated them with the ARAS PLM Tool to manage the life cycle workflow of ECU and Power-train software issues.
- Collaborated with the design team to develop Windows app utilizing C# WinForms for extracting Bill of Materials parts within the Teamcenter tool.
- Developed a drawing material extraction DLL in .NET framework for seamless integration with NX-CAD Automation.
- Migrated ASP.NET Web Forms app to Microsoft Power app, enabling employees to exchange greetings within organization.

Last updated: May 26, 2024